Gode von Aesch, Alexander; Papers ger107
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Alexander Gode Von Aesch Papers
1924-1987
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Gode, Alexander, 1906-1970
ger107
6 cubic ft.
Includes biographical information, photographs, correspondence, writings, and periodicals related to Alexander Gode von Aesch.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives 2001
Organizational Sketch
Born in Bremen in the German Empire in 1906, Gode emigrated to the United States in the 1920s. He became a notable linguist and helped develop the internationalist Interlingua language.
Scope and Contents
The Alexander Gode von Aesch collection includes biographical information, photographs, and correspondence. There are also writings by Alexander Gode von Aesch and others as well as various issues of periodicals with references to Gode von Aesch. Related collections include New York City's Storm Publishers and the Frederick Ungar Papers.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection has three topical series, each arranged alphabetically.
Literature; World War, 1939-1945 -- Refugees.; Publishers and publishing.; Gode, Alexander, 1906-1970; Gode von Aesch, Anna.; Gode von Aesch, Marilyn.; Caille, Pierre.; Storm Publishers.
- Writings by A. Gode von Aesch, 1924-1980; 1; 3.5 cubic ft.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  Writings personally authored by A. Gode von Aesch and other personal material.
  - Biographical material - vitae, death certificate, award certificates, letter with biographical information, 1930 and 1931 cruise ship passenger lists, etc., 1930-1931; Undated (Box 1 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Item 1)
  - Photographs, Undated (Box 1 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Item 2)
  - Photographs, Undated (Box 1 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Item 3)
  - Photograph - Caille, Pierre, Undated (Box 1 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Item 4)
  - Notebooks and Diaries, 15 items, various formats and sizes, Undated (Box 1 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Item 5)
  - Photographs, some in albums, several hundred, Undated (Box 1 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Item 6)
  - Correspondence with Anna Gode von Aesch, Undated (Box 2 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 1)
  - Correspondence - Gode Family, Undated (Box 2 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 2)
  - Correspondence - Archivos Peruanos de Patologia y Clinica, Undated (Box 2 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 3)
  - Correspondence - "Live Chitchat", Undated (Box 2 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 4)
  - Correspondence - First International Translation Prize, Undated (Box 2 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 5)
  - Correspondence - Pertaining to Allison Gode Bertschee's mother, Undated (Box 2 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 6)
  - Correspondence - "Just Words" (1 of 2), Undated (Box 2 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 7)
  - Correspondence - "Just Words" (2 of 2), Undated (Box 2 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 8)
  - Correspondence - Letters of Condolence, Undated (Box 2 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 9)
  - Correspondence - "Of Words and Things", Undated (Box 2 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1924-1942 (Box 2 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1960-1970 (Box 2 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1970-1980 (Box 2 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 13)
  - Correspondence - Hardin, Floyd and Evelyn (Friends of the International Language), Undated (Box 2 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 14)
  - Correspondence with daughter, Marilyn (Bepsie) (1 of 4), Undated (Box 2 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 15)
  - Correspondence with daughter, Marilyn (Bepsie) (2 of 4), Undated (Box 2 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 16)
  - Correspondence with daughter, Marilyn (Bepsie) (3 of 4), Undated (Box 2 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 17)
  - Correspondence with daughter, Marilyn (Bepsie) (4 of 4), Undated (Box 2 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 18)
  - Letter to Peter L. Lersch, with 1929 advance copy of "Sex Truths for Men and Women", Undated (Box 2 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 19)
  - Letter to teachers of German, 1956 December (Box 2 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 20)
  - "Interlingua" 4 page description of the work, Undated (Box 2 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 21)
  - "Summario in Interlingua" capitula I-IV, Undated (Box 2 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 22)
  - Unknown pamphlet in Russian issued by Science Service, Interlingua Division, 1964 (Box 2 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 23)
  - Materials relating to Henry Seager, Undated (Box 2 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 24)
  - International Auxiliary Language Association (1945 Annual Report, pamphlet about Interlingua), Undated (Box 2 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 25)
  - American Translators Association, By-laws and Code of Ethical Practices and Professional Rights; Budget materials, 1972 (Box 2 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 26)
  - American Translators Association, Membership List, 1975 (Box 2 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 27)
  - American Translators Association, Miscellaneous publications/reports, Undated (Box 2 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 28)
  - American Translators Association, Annual Meeting, Proceedings, 1963 (Box 2 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 29)
  - American Translators Association, Panel Discussion from 12th Annual Convention, "Poetic Translation", 1971 (Box 2 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 30)
  - American Translators Association, Professional Services Directory, 1969 (Box 2 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 31)
  - JAMA Interlingua Tear Sheets, Undated (Box 2 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 32)
  - Book invoices, 1950-1953 (Box 2 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 33)
  - Publishers' Book Advertisements, Undated (Box 2 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 34)
  - American Medical Writers' Association. Report from the Publications Committee to the Board of Directors Meeting, 1967 (Box 2 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 35)
  - Guild of Professional Translators, Translator Referral Directory, 1975-1976 (Box 2 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 36)
  - Writings by A. Gode von Aesch, Undated (Box 2 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 37)
  - Book Review, Ernesto Che Guevara, by David Allport (2 copies), Undated (Box 2 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 38)
  - Typescripts for unknown column, 1961 (Box 2 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 39)
  - "Just Words," Typescripts, nos. 5-300, 1962-1967 (Box 2 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 40)
  - Just Words, typescripts, nos. 301-369, 1967-1969 (Box 3 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 1)
  - Just Words (offprints from JAMA), 1962-1972 (Box 3 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 2)
  - Just Words (suggestions, comments), Undated (Box 3 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 3)
  - Live Chitchat, typescripts, 1963-1965 (Box 3 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 4)
  - Live Chitchat (from Lebende Sprachen), Undated (Box 3 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 5)
  - Of Words and Things, typescripts, nos. Jan-69, 1962-1963 (Box 3 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 6)
  - Of Words and Things, typescripts, nos. 85-106, 1964 (Box 3 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 7)
  - Offprint - A Beautiful Day (from Quinto Lingo), 1967 September (Box 3 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 8)
  - Offprint - Goethes 'Seefahrt' (from Monatshefte), 1949 February (Box 3 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 9)
  - Offprint - Makarie (from Monatshefte fur Deutschen Unterricht), Undated (Box 3 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 10)
  - Offprint - A Note on Iambs and Trochees, (from Monatshefte fur Deutschen Unterricht), ca. 1939 (Box 3 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 11)
  - Offprint - Readings and Misreadings of Fritz von Unruh's The End Is Not Yet, (from Modern Language Forum, Undated (Box 3 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 12)
  - Speech given at the Annual Meeting of the American Translators Association, 1962 November 30 (Box 3 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 13)
  - Speech given at a meeting of the American Translators' Society Association, 1966 (Box 3 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 14)
  - Speeches given at the Annual Meeting of the American Translators Association (2 copies), 1968 October 26 (Box 3 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 15)
  - Der Deutsche in Amerika (by A. Gode von Aesch?), Undated (Box 3 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 16)
  - In Search of the International Auxiliary Language, by E. Clark Stillman and Alexander Gode. International Auxiliary Language Association, undated 6p. (Box 3 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 17)
  - Interlingua; a grammar of the international language, prepared by A. Gode and H.E. Blair. 2nd. edition. Storm Publishers, 1955 (Box 3 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 18)
  - Interlingua-English; a dictionary of the international language, prepared by the research staff of the International Auxiliary Language Association, under the direction of Alexander Gode (2 copies), 1951 (Box 3 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 19)
  - Interlinguistic Standardization, by E. Clark Stillman and A. Gode von Aesch (typescript), 1943 (Box 3 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 20)
  - Principles for a Schematic IAL, Folder also contains several typescripts related to this work, 1940 June (Box 3 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 21)
  - Rhyming Dictionary of Interlingua, by Hugh E. Blair, with the assistance of Alexander Gode and others(2 copies of typescript), 1951 (Box 4 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 1)
  - "Schuld und Suhne des Ubersetzers," beitrag zum Siebenten Germanistentag New York, Sonnabend, den, 1966 April 30 (Box 4 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 2)
  - Tannenberg, by Theobald von Schafer. Translation by A. Gode von Aesch, 1928 (Box 4 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 3)
  - Tonio Kroger, by Thomas Mann. Translation by A. Gode von Aesch (3 copies of typescript), Undated (Box 4 (1-Writings by A. Gode von Aesch), Folder 4)
- Writings by others, 1931-1987; 2; 1.25 cubic ft.
  Related writings by other authors, some contain annotations/corrections by Gode von Aesch.
  - Burkhard, Arthur. "Conrad Ferdinand Meyer in Recent Translation," ( Reprinted from The Modern Language Journal, no. 8, 1931 (Box 4 (2-Writings by others), Folder 5)
  - Campbell, Stuart B., tr. "Trans le Speculo e lo que Alice Trovava Ibi per Lewis Carroll,", Undated (Box 4 (2-Writings by others), Folder 6)
  - Collinson, Wm. E. "Word-Building in International Language," IALA, Undated (Box 4 (2-Writings by others), Folder 7)
  - Crandell, T. Ellen. "Translators and Translating; Selected Essays from the American Translators Association Summer Workshops,", 1974 (Box 4 (2-Writings by others), Folder 8)
  - Curtius, Ernst R. Europaische Literatur und Lateinisches Mittelalter, A. Francke, 1948 (Box 4 (2-Writings by others), Folder 9)
  - Eaton, Helen S. Semantic Frequency List for English, French, German, and Spanish, University of Chicago Press, 1940 (Box 4 (2-Writings by others), Folder 10)
  - Fife, Robert H. "Outline and Bibliography of German Literature during the Classical Period," Columbia University (contains annotations by Gode), 1935 (Box 5 (2-Writings by others), Folder 1)
  - Fife, Robert H. "Outline and Bibliography of German Literature from the Renaissance to the Age of Enlightenment," Columbia University (Contains annotations by Gode), 1932 (Box 5 (2-Writings by others), Folder 2)
  - Fischbach, Henry. "Abbreviations in the German, French, and Italian Literature," (Reprinted from Advances in Chemistry Series, No. 10), 1954 (Box 5 (2-Writings by others), Folder 3)
  - Fischbach, Henry. "Biomedical, Pharmacological, and Medical Terminology in French and German Chemical Literature," (Reprinted from Advances in Chemistry Series, No. 16), 1956 (Box 5 (2-Writings by others), Folder 4)
  - Friederici, Hans-Joachim. Das Unternehmen Vennbahn, 33p., Undated (Box 5 (2-Writings by others), Folder 5)
  - Gilbert, Henry. Caius Ist ein Dummkopf, 74p. (typescript), Undated (Box 5 (2-Writings by others), Folder 6)
  - Gopsill, F.P. and B.C. Sexton. Concise English-Interlingua Dictionary, British Interlingua Society, 1987 (Box 5 (2-Writings by others), Folder 7)
  - "Guide to Russian Medical Literature," U.S. Dept. of Health, Education and Welfare, 1958 (Box 5 (2-Writings by others), Folder 8)
  - Hofmann, Erich. Sprachwissenschaftliche Bibliographie (typescript), 1933 (Box 5 (2-Writings by others), Folder 9)
  - Lange, Victor. [Bibliography on the Biedermeier period], Undated (Box 5 (2-Writings by others), Folder 10)
  - Liedke, Herbert R. "Vom Wesen und Wortschatz der Autosprache," (Reprinted from Monatshefte fur Deutschen Unterricht), Undated (Box 5 (2-Writings by others), Folder 11)
  - "La Lingvo Internacia," (Reprinted from Esperanto-Jahrbuch), Undated (Box 5 (2-Writings by others), Folder 12)
  - Merritt, Anna J. "Pabst and the Film: a Retrospective," 4p., Undated (Box 5 (2-Writings by others), Folder 13)
  - Merritt, Richard L. "Politische Desintegration und die Offentliche Wirtschaft: Das Dilemma Berlins," 18p., Undated (Box 5 (2-Writings by others), Folder 14)
  - Mitrovich, Paul. Un Esay de Interlingvistiqe, 1969 (Box 5 (2-Writings by others), Folder 15)
  - Modern Language Association. "Historical and Cultural Survey on the German-Americans,", ca. 1940 (Box 5 (2-Writings by others), Folder 16)
  - Modern Language Association. "Relations of Literature and Science,", 1940 (Box 5 (2-Writings by others), Folder 17)
  - "Pathology - Ward," typed manuscript with correction (author and editor unknown), Undated (Box 5 (2-Writings by others), Folder 18)
  - Pocar, Ervino. "Traduzioni dal Tedesco, 1920-1970,", Undated (Box 5 (2-Writings by others), Folder 19)
  - Podobsky, Jaroslav. "Johannes Amos Comenius," Storm, 1958 (Box 5 (2-Writings by others), Folder 20)
  - Schaeffer, Albrecht. Rudolf Erzerum oder Des Lebens Einfachheit, 294p. (typescript), Undated (Box 5 (2-Writings by others), Folder 21)
  - Sholiton, Robert D. "A Set of Pattern Drills to Accompany H.G. Lunt's Fundamentals of Russian,", 1963 (Box 5 (2-Writings by others), Folder 22)
  - "Terminarium" (IT 3804), Undated (Box 5 (2-Writings by others), Folder 23)
  - "Trasylol" (articles by various authors from unknown source), Undated (Box 5 (2-Writings by others), Folder 24)
  - "Ubersetzen - selbstlose Kunst und muhsames Handwerk," (Reprinted from Der Junge Buchhandel), 1969 November 6 (Box 5 (2-Writings by others), Folder 25)
  - Wagner, Lydia E. The Scientific Interest of Friedrich vin Hardenberg (Novalis Edwards Brothers, 1937 (Box 5 (2-Writings by others), Folder 26)
  - Wilgenhof, K. "Dictionario de Nomines Geographic in Interlingua", Undated (Box 5 (2-Writings by others), Folder 27)
  - Wilgenhof, K. Grammatica de Interlingua,, Information Interlingua, 1973 (Box 5 (2-Writings by others), Folder 28)
- Periodical Issues, 1934-1976; 3; 1.25 cubic ft.
  Periodicals with references to A. Gode von Aesch.
  - American Scholar, autumn, 1951 (Box 5 (3-Periodical Issues), Folder 29)
  - American Translator, no. 1; no. 3 (both contain articles by Gode), 1966-1967 (Box 5 (3-Periodical Issues), Folder 30)
  - Der Auslanddeutsche, heft 2, 1934 (Box 5 (3-Periodical Issues), Folder 31)
  - The ATA Chronicle, 15 issues, 1970-1978 (Box 5 (3-Periodical Issues), Folder 32)
  - Babel, 13 issues (no. 2, 1962 contains article by A. Gode), 1962-1975 (Box 5 (3-Periodical Issues), Folder 33)
  - The Bible Translator, nos. 1-4; nos. 1-2, 1974-1975 (Box 5 (3-Periodical Issues), Folder 34)
  - Bibliographia de Interlingua, no. 1 (cites some of A. Gode's publications), 1974 (Box 6 (3-Periodical Issues), Folder 1)
  - Bulletin d'Information de la Chambre Belge des Traducteurs, Interpretes et Philologues, no. 3, 1976 (Box 6 (3-Periodical Issues), Folder 2)
  - Currero, no. 22 (contains article on the death of A. Gode), 1970 (Box 6 (3-Periodical Issues), Folder 3)
  - Equivalences, no. 2, 1973 (Box 6 (3-Periodical Issues), Folder 4)
  - The Federal Linguist, 1973-1974 (Box 6 (3-Periodical Issues), Folder 5)
  - Fremdsprache, 1972-1976 (Box 6 (3-Periodical Issues), Folder 6)
  - The Germanic Review(all contain book reviews by A. Gode von Aesch, 1938-1944 (Box 6 (3-Periodical Issues), Folder 7)
  - Interlingua Institute Newsletter, 1974 (Box 6 (3-Periodical Issues), Folder 8)
  - L'Interprete, 9 issues, 1963-1976 (Box 6 (3-Periodical Issues), Folder 9)
  - Journal des Traducteurs, no. 1, no. 3, 1962 (Box 6 (3-Periodical Issues), Folder 10)
  - Le Linguiste de Taalkundige, 13 issues, 1972-1975 (Box 6 (3-Periodical Issues), Folder 11)
  - META, 1972-1976 (Box 6 (3-Periodical Issues), Folder 12)
  - Mitteilungsblatt Bulletin Bollettino, 4 issues, 1972-1974 (Box 6 (3-Periodical Issues), Folder 13)
  - Mitteilunggsblatt fur Dolmetscher und Ubersetzer, 3 issues, ca. 1970-1979 (Box 6 (3-Periodical Issues), Folder 14)
  - The Modern Language Forum, no. 1-2; no. 3-4 (both issues contain articles by A. Gode von Aesch), 1949-1950 (Box 6 (3-Periodical Issues), Folder 15)
  - "Neue Bucher," Nr. 1/2, 1934 (Box 6 (3-Periodical Issues), Folder 16)
  - Novas de Interlingua, no.7 (A. Gode, editor), 1965 (Box 6 (3-Periodical Issues), Folder 17)
  - The Open Court, 1932 April (Box 6 (3-Periodical Issues), Folder 18)
  - Revista de Interlingua, nos. 33-34, no. 44, 1969-1970 (Box 6 (3-Periodical Issues), Folder 19)
  - Traduire, no.70, nos. 79-81, no. 81-82, 1972-1975 (Box 6 (3-Periodical Issues), Folder 20)
  - Translation, 1973-1983 (Box 6 (3-Periodical Issues), Folder 21)
  - Translation Inquirer, 21 issues, 1962-1968 (Box 6 (3-Periodical Issues), Folder 22)
  - Translator no.1 (contains article by A. Gode), 1963 (Box 6 (3-Periodical Issues), Folder 23)
  - Translatoren, 14 issues, 1972-1976 (Box 6 (3-Periodical Issues), Folder 24)
  - Der Ubersetzer, 18 issues, 1973 May-1975 July (Box 6 (3-Periodical Issues), Folder 25)